Guide to the Glenway Wescott Collection of Nelson Lansdale Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Glenway Wescott collection of Nelson Lansdale papers
1936-1951
YCAL MSS 149
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.68
(4 boxes)
The collection contains correspondence, manuscripts, and other personal items relating to a period of Lansdale's life between 1936-1951, including his work for Newsweek magazine.
Lansdale, Nelson
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Received with the Glenway Wescott Papers, purchase from Monroe Wheeler, 1988.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Associated Materials
Additional Nelson Lansdale material can be found in the Glenway Wescott Papers [YCAL MSS 134]. The materials in this collection are the contents of a box of Lansdale's papers given to Glenway Wescott for safekeeping.
NELSON LANSDALE
Nelson Lansdale, freelance writer and arts columnist for Newsweek magazine, was a close friend of Glenway Wescott.
Scope and Contents
The Glenway Wescott Collection of Nelson Lansdale Papers contain correspondence, manuscripts, and other personal items relating to Lansdale's life between 1936-1951.
The collection is housed in four boxes and is organized into three series: I. Correspondence; II. Writings; and III. Other Material.
Series I, Correspondence, consists of incoming and outgoing letters, mostly to family members and close friends of Lansdale's, concentrated in the early 1940s. The subject of the letters is divided between Lansdale's personal life and his military service in World War II.
Series II. Writings, is divided into two subseries. The first, Interview and Research Notes for Newsweek Articles, contains source material gathered by Lansdale for the magazine. General Writings contains free-lance articles and early creative writing efforts.
Series III. Other Material includes a diary, financial papers, notebooks, and telephone books, among other items.
Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Journalists -- United States; Lansdale, Nelson; Wescott, Glenway, 1901-1987; Newsweek
- Correspondence, 1936-1951; Series I; 0.42; (1 box)
  - Besler, Max, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    To and From NL
  - Brittain, William James, 1937 Sep 11 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    From NL
  - Clarke, A. W., Jr., 1942-44, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 3-4)
  - Coffman, George R., 1940 May 7 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Constantine, Mildred, 1940 May 13 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    To NL
  - Fernandez, Frank E., 1942 Feb 27 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Finley, David E., Mr. and Mrs., 1940-41 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Hibbs, Ben, 1944 Mar 11 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Hill, Geo A., Jr., Mrs., n.d. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Holme, Bryan, 1942 May 27 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Isherwood, Christopher, 1939 Mar 28 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Kieffer, S., 1942 Mar 8 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Kirstein, Lincoln, 1941 Aug 21 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Klonis, Stewart, 1939 Mar 28 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Lindley, Ernest, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Lynes, George Platt, 1940 May 14 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - McAndrew, John, 1942 Jan 9 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Macartney, Paul B., 1941 Mar 14 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - May, Marguerite, 1944 Mar 14 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Morgan, R., 1941 Feb 12 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Morse, Grace, 1936 Oct 9 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - New York State Department of Taxation and Finance, 1939-40 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Phillips, Frances, 1942-42 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Potts, Richard, Mr. and Mrs., 1942 Jan 25 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Schaefer, Bertha, 1941 Apr 26 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Sherwood, Harry, 1940 Jul 8 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Smith, John Francis, Jr., Mrs., n.d. (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Stout, Wesley W., 1941 Sep 10 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Thurber, Mrs., 1946 Aug 18 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Trail, William E., 1939-40 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Wescott, Glenway, 1941, 1944, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Whiting, F. A., Jr., 1940 May 20 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Unidentified
    - "Auntie", 1939-42 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - "Brinton", 1940-44 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - "Coz", 1939-41 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - "E. C.", 1939-40, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - "Emily", 1940-41 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - "Flete Feete", 1941 Jun 16 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - "Mary Margaret, Harry and Elizabeth", 1936-42 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - "Mother and Dad", 1936-41, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 41-42)
    - "Mac", 1939-40 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - "Pat", 1940-41, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - "Rosemary", 1939-44 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - "Ted", 1940-41 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Unidentified, 1936-51, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Correspondence re: Military service in World War II, 1942-43 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Unfinished drafts of letters, 1936, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Empty envelopes, 1940-44, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 50)
- Writings, 1936-1942; Series II; 0.84; (2 boxes)
  - INTERVIEW AND RESEARCH NOTES FOR NEWSWEEK ARTICLES
    - Mme. Claude Alphaud, 1942 Jan 27 (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - American Artists Group, Inc., 1939 Oct 26 (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - Americana Research, 1941 Oct 8 (Box 2, Folder 53)
    - Alexander Archipenko, 1939 May 25 (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - Juan Arvizu, 1941 Mar 25 (Box 2, Folder 55)
    - Ballet Roundup, 1940 Mar 27 (Box 2, Folder 56)
    - Rainey Bennett, 1940 Jan 26 (Box 2, Folder 57)
    - Brick Bank, 1940 Jan 29 (Box 2, Folder 58)
    - Richmond Barthe, 1939 Jun 8 (Box 2, Folder 59)
    - Aaron Bohrod, 1939 Oct 25 (Box 2, Folder 60)
    - Mortimer Brandt, 1939 Dec 7 (Box 2, Folder 61)
    - Brandt Gallery, 1941 Jun 24 (Box 2, Folder 62)
    - Benjamin Britten, 1941 Mar 27 (Box 2, Folder 63)
    - Carnegie Intitute Research, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 64)
    - James Chapin, 1940 Feb 29 (Box 2, Folder 65)
    - Minna Citron, 1941 Dec 17 (Box 2, Folder 66)
    - Xavier Cugat, 1941 Sep 30 (Box 2, Folder 67)
    - Chester Dale Collection, 1941 Nov 12 (Box 2, Folder 68)
    - Goode Davis, 1939 Dec 14 (Box 2, Folder 69)
    - Dean Dixon, 1941 Jun 18 (Box 2, Folder 70)
    - Clarence Carter, 1939 Oct 17 (Box 2, Folder 71)
    - Eddy Duchin, 1940 Sep 12 (Box 2, Folder 72)
    - English Art, 1939 ar 3 (Box 2, Folder 73)
    - Faberge / Victor Hammer, 1939 Dec 13 (Box 2, Folder 74)
    - Shep Fields, 1941 Sep 9 (Box 2, Folder 75)
    - First National Soldier-Artist Exhibition, 1941 Sept 16 (Box 2, Folder 76)
    - Jean Gauguin, 1939 May 4 (Box 2, Folder 77)
    - Glass, 1939 Dec 20 (Box 2, Folder 78)
    - Morton Gould, 1940 Mar 26 (Box 2, Folder 79)
    - George Grosz, 1939 Nov 1 (Box 2, Folder 80)
    - Mrs. Charles S. Guggenheimer, 1941 Apr 23 (Box 2, Folder 81)
    - John Henry Hammond, Jr., 1940 Sep 16 (Box 2, Folder 82)
    - Hawaiian Music / Ray Kinney, 1940 Oct 1 (Box 2, Folder 83)
    - Bernard Herrmann, 1940 Apr 2 (Box 2, Folder 84)
    - Hole Collection, [1939] Dec 20 (Box 2, Folder 85)
    - Peter Hurd, 1939 Apr 11 (Box 2, Folder 86)
    - Eastman Jonson, 1940 Jan 9 (Box 2, Folder 87)
    - Jacob Jordaens, 1940 Feb 7 (Box 2, Folder 88)
    - Eliasz Kanarek, 1940 Jan 23 (Box 2, Folder 89)
    - Fritz Kreisler, 1940 Mar 13 (Box 2, Folder 90)
    - Kress Art Collection, 1939 Jul 13 (Box 2, Folder 91)
    - Walt Kuhn, 1941 Mar 2 (Box 2, Folder 92)
    - Walt Kuhn, 1941 Nov 26 (Box 2, Folder 93)
    - Jim Longtree, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 94)
    - Tilly Losch, 1940 Jul 7 (Box 2, Folder 95)
    - Luxembourg Museum, 1939 Jul 19 (Box 2, Folder 96)
    - George Platt Lynes, 1940 Jan 19 (Box 2, Folder 97)
    - MacDowell Colony, 1939 Apr 25 (Box 2, Folder 98)
    - W. Somerset Maugham, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 99)
    - Nathan Milstein, 1942 Feb 10 (Box 2, Folder 100)
    - Joan Miro, 1939 Apr (Box 2, Folder 101)
    - Mystery Research, 1939 Oct 19 (Box 2, Folder 102)
    - William Bayard Okie, Jr., 1939 Oct 4 (Box 2, Folder 103)
    - Jan Pearce, 1941 Nov 26 (Box 2, Folder 104)
    - Philadelphia Story / Atwater Kent, 1939 Jun 20 (Box 2, Folder 105)
    - Picasso, 1939 Nov 16 (Box 2, Folder 106)
    - RCA Victor Magic Brain Phonograph, 1941 Jul 29 (Box 2, Folder 107)
    - Edward G. Robinson, 1939 Jul 31 (Box 2, Folder 108)
    - Rodgers and Hart, 1940 Apr 2 (Box 2, Folder 109)
    - Paul Rosenberg, 1941 Nov 4 (Box 2, Folder 110)
    - Patsy Santo, 1940 Jan 16 (Box 2, Folder 111)
    - Kurt Schindler Book, 1941 Jul 29 (Box 2, Folder 112)
    - William Schuman, 1940 Jul 2 (Box 2, Folder 113)
    - Roy Shaw, 1939 May 9 (Box 2, Folder 114)
    - Sheeler Television Broadcast, 1939 Oct 6 (Box 2, Folder 115)
    - Alfred Jenkins Shriver, 1939 Oct 26 (Box 2, Folder 116)
    - Maurice Sterne, 1939 Dec 19 (Box 2, Folder 117)
    - Swedish Art Exhibition, 1939 Jul 26 (Box 2, Folder 118)
    - Patrick Taccard, 1939 Apr 5 (Box 2, Folder 119)
    - Richard Taylor, 1941 Dec 11 (Box 2, Folder 120)
    - Maurice de Vlaminck, 1940 Feb 27 (Box 2, Folder 121)
    - Lynd Ward, 1939 Mar 28 (Box 2, Folder 122)
  - GENERAL MANUSCRIPTS
    - Aristophanes and Moliere, draft, typescript, corrected (Box 3, Folder 123)
    - Aristotle and Winterset, draft, typescript, corrected, 1936 (Box 3, Folder 124)
    - "The Ballet Good Thing for Painters", printed version, ArtNews, 1941 Oct (Box 3, Folder 125)
    - Review of "The Dark Island" by Vita Sackville-West, draft, typescript, corrected (Box 3, Folder 126)
    - A Dissertation upon Roast Lamb (with mint sauce), draft, typescript, corrected, 1936 Mar 25 (Box 3, Folder 127)
      Includes rejection letter
    - A Fool and his Friends are Soon Parted, draft, typescript, corrected (Box 3, Folder 128)
    - Happy Man, draft, typescript, corrected (Box 3, Folder 129)
    - The High Priest (1888-, draft, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 130)
      re: T.S. Eliot
    - It Can't Happen Here, draft, typescript, ca. 1942 Feb (Box 3, Folder 131)
      Includes rejection letter and postcard
    - Location Central, draft, typescript, ca. 1937 Oct (Box 3, Folder 132)
    - The "Lost" Schumann Concerto, drafts, typescript, ca. 1937 Dec (Box 3, Folder 133-134)
      Includes rejection letters
    - "Not I But Beethoven", draft, typescript, corrected, ca. 1938 Oct (Box 3, Folder 135)
    - Notes for profile of Lincoln Kirstein for Dance Magazine, 1941 Jul (Box 3, Folder 136)
    - Note on Buell Mullen, draft, typescript carbon (Box 3, Folder 137)
    - Obviously, draft, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 138)
    - Orchestra Seat, draft, typescript carbon, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 139-140)
    - The Perfect Angel, draft, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 141)
    - PHI BETA KAPPA, draft, typescript, ca. 1936 Oct (Box 3, Folder 142)
    - The Plague, drafts, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 143-144)
    - Poems: Cityscape, Broadcast, and Rehearsal, drafts, typescript, ca. 1937 Dec (Box 3, Folder 145)
    - Poems and ideas for writings, drafts, typescript (Box 3, Folder 146)
    - The Poor are Always with Us", draft, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 147)
    - Poor Soil, draft, typescript, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 148)
    - Schubert, draft, typescript, corrected, 1941 Feb 1 (Box 3, Folder 149)
      With concert program
    - So You're Going to Hell?, draft, typescript, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 150)
    - The Stage is Set: Seven Seasons of Decor on Broadway, drafts, typescript carbon, corrected, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 151-152)
      Includes cover letter to "Emily"
    - A Tale of Two People, draft, typescript, carbon, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 153)
    - Decor at the Opera, drafts, typescript carbon, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 154)
    - Decor at the Opera, printed version, as: "To the Dawn of Better Decor at the Opera", ArtNews, 1942 Mar (Box 3, Folder 155)
    - Unfinished Symphony, draft, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 156)
    - Manuscript fragments, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 157)
- Other Material, 1936-1942; Series III; 0.42; (1 box)
  - Calendar pages, annotated, 1940 (Box 4, Folder 158)
  - Diary, 1942 (Box 4, Folder 159)
  - Financial papers, 1936-42 (Box 4, Folder 160)
  - Instructions from Glenway Wescott re: Nelson Lansdale Papers, 1942 Apr 20 (Box 4, Folder 161)
  - Lists, ca. 1938-40 (Box 4, Folder 162)
  - Memo from Surgeon General re: WAVES [parody], n.d. (Box 4, Folder 163)
  - Notebooks, ca. 1937-39 (Box 4, Folder 164)
  - Notes, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 165)
  - Postcard: "The Old Homestead", n.d. (Box 4, Folder 166)
  - Telephone books, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 167)